Finding Aid for the Elmer Belt Collection of Vinciana Graphic Arts LSC.2366
UCLA Library Special Collections
Elmer Belt collection of Vinciana graphic arts
circa 1510-19th century
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2366
14 linear feet
The Elmer Belt collection of Vinciana graphic arts is a special collection of original artwork, original printed lithographs, and materials concerning Leonardo da Vinci and the Italian Renaissance. It was donated to UCLA in 1961 by Dr. Elmer Belt, Professor Emeritus in the UCLA School of Medicine and a collector of Vinciana for more than sixty years.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Elmer Belt, 1961.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9997055638706533
Biographical / Historical
Elmer Belt, M.D. (1893-1980), was a Los Angeles area urologist, bibliophile, and humanist who was instrumental in the founding of the School of Medicine, University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA). An avid book collector, Dr. Belt became an expert on Leonardo da Vinci and his time, amassing a large and important collection of books and other material related to da Vinci's life and work. He donated this collection to UCLA in 1961. Born Arthur Elmer Belt in Chicago, Illinois on April 10, 1893, his family moved to Los Angeles when he was nine and then to a small ranch in Orange County near Anaheim. Elmer Belt (the form of name he preferred) entered Los Angeles High School in 1907 and enrolled in Latin, a medical school prerequisite. There he met Ruth Smart whom, he said, he "never subsequently permitted out of my sight." The two were married in 1918. Dr. Belt began collecting books as a student in 1909 with works by Upton Sinclair; in 1934 he became involved with Sinclair's campaign for governor of California. The Upton Sinclair collection was eventually donated to Occidental College. Dr. Belt attended the University of California at Berkeley, obtaining a B.A. in 1916 and an M.A. in 1917. He attended the University of California Medical School in San Francisco and was chosen as a fellow of the Hooper Institute for Medical Research, working with Dr. George Whipple and Dr. Frank Hinman. After finishing medical school in 1920 Dr. Belt continued working in urology with Dr. Hinman. Early in his medical school career, Dr. Belt signed up for a non-credit elective course in the History of Medicine taught by Dr. George Washington Corner, an anatomist who had recently come to the University of California from Johns Hopkins University. It was in this class that Dr. Belt developed his fascination with and devotion to Leonardo da Vinci, inspiring the vast library of Vinciana he eventually donated to UCLA. Subsequently his collecting fervor also included Silas Weir Mitchell and Florence Nightingale and in the 1930s Dr. Belt began working with Los Angeles bookseller Jake Zeitlin to fulfill these and other ambitious collecting interests. After a year as Resident in Urology with Dr. Hinman in San Francisco, Dr. Belt spent a year as Resident in General Surgery at Boston's Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, working under Dr. Harvey Cushing. In 1923, the Belts moved to Los Angeles where Elmer began a private practice. He soon established the Elmer Belt Urologic Group, a group practice which moved to its own building on Wilshire Boulevard in 1936; the upper floor of this structure housed his ever-expanding library. From 1939 through 1954 Belt served as the President of the State Board of Public Health, having been first appointed by California Governor Culbert Olsen and then reappointed by Governor Earl Warren for each of Warren's three terms in office. Dr. Belt had privileges as a staff, attending, or consulting urologist at many hospitals around Los Angeles County and taught as Clinical Professor of Surgery (Urology) in the UCLA School of Medicine. He was instrumental in the founding of the UCLA School of Medicine and finding its first dean, and continued as its staunch supporter throughout his life. Elmer Belt died on May 17, 1980 at age 87.
Scope and Contents
The Elmer Belt collection of Vinciana graphic arts is a special collection of original artwork, original printed lithographs, and materials concerning Leonardo da Vinci and the Italian Renaissance. It was donated to UCLA in 1961 by Dr. Elmer Belt, Professor Emeritus in the UCLA School of Medicine and a collector of Vinciana for more than sixty years.
Arrangement
The arrangement of materials maintains their existing order.
Related Materials
Elmer Belt papers (Collection 0066). Available at Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, UCLA.
Charles Huggins collection of material about and correspondence with Elmer Belt and Willard E. Goodwin (Collection 0043). Available at Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, UCLA.
Jake Zeitlin papers (Collection 0334). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
John Allison Benjamin papers (Collection 0001). Available at Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, UCLA.
Kate Traumann Steinitz papers (Collection 1770). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Library. Arts Library. Publications. (Collection 0164). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, University Archives, University of California, Los Angeles.
Mae Babitz papers (Collection 1740). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Sir William Osler Portrait by Seymour Thomas and Other Osler-Related Papers (Collection 0181). Available at Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, UCLA.
Willard E. Goodwin papers (Collection 0573). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
- Head of a horse, circa 1510; lsc_2366_b001_001; Melzi, Francesco, 1491 or 1493-approximately 1570; Italian drawing. After the Antique. Red chalk.; Height left 12.8 cm; height right 12 cm. Width top: 12 cm; bottom: 12.8 cm.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Acquired at Hauswedell, Hamburg 1956 as "Milanese drawing."
  Scope and Contents
  Watermark: Possibly drawn after the Roman Horse in Naples. Attributed to Melzi in 1967 by Carlo Pedretti.
  Bibliography
  Barbara Bacall, A catalogue of the drawings of Leonardo da Vinci and his school in the United States of America, M.A. thesis, UCLA, 1968; Carlo Pedretti, Leonardo da Vinci: studies for a Nativity and the 'Mona Lisa Cartoon' with drawings after Leonardo from the Elmer Belt Library of Vinciana: exhibition in honour of the Elmer Belt, M.D. on the occasion of his eightieth birthday (Los Angeles: UCLA, 1973) (UCLA Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies. Publication Number 6), pp. 39f.
- Grotesque heads, circa 1510; lsc_2366_b001_002; Melzi, Francesco, 1491 or 1493-approximately 1570; Italian drawings. After da Vinci. Pen and brown ink over very light lead point.; Top: 5.6 x 10.5 cm; bottom: 4.6 x 10.3 cm.
  Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Edward Fowles, 1969.
  Custodial History
  Leonardo's originals were in the collection of the Duke of Devonshire at Chatsworth; original Leonardo of lower left figure purchased by Getty Museum in 1984. Formerly a part of a set of twelve in the collection of the Earl of Pembroke at Wilton House.
  Two fragments in one mount. Each fragment contains two grotesque heads facing each other in profile. Counterimage of upper right figure in Conte de Caylus (q.v.) No. 25.
  F[rances] F[inger] in UCLA Librarian 22(2)(February 1969):7-9; S.A. Strong, Reproductions in facsimile of the drawings by the Old Masters in the collection of the Earl of Pembroke and Montgomery at Wilton House...(London, 1900), Part II, no. 15; Pedretti (op.cit.in I.1) p. 40.
- Female figure, 16th century; lsc_2366_b001_003; Parmigianino, 1503-1540; Italian drawing. Brown pen and ink on brown paper, heightened with white.; 28 x 15 cm.
- Last Supper, circa 1562; lsc_2366_b001_004; Figino, Girolamo; Italian drawing. After da Vinci. Crayon and red chalk.; 13 x 19.5 cm.
  Federn Collection.
  Left below the ink: 104. Right below: collector's mark. Verso: Stamp of V.F. der Collection Federn (Lugt 923) and in fine ink script: Nov.6-046-la. Below the Federn stamp a pale red stamp: V.M. Left along upper half of page: Leonardo da Vinci. In the middle of the fold: 277'. The verso shows that the leaf was once folded. Upper: Study after Dioscurides of the Quirinal. Lower: Studies of baroque baldacchino columns. Attribution: Carlo Pedretti.
  Bacall (op.cit. in I.1).
- Four grotesque figures, 17th century; lsc_2366_b001_005; Ghezzi, Giuseppe, 1634-1721; Italian drawing. Sepia. Watermark, Left: 1431 Right: Belt no. 55-307.; 12 x 19.5 cm.
  Acquired in 1955.
  Verso: handwritten address: "All'ill R Y...al sig Cardinale d'Este Modena" Stripe of paper attached to lower margin with signature: "Ghezzi."
- Cain and Abel, 17th century; lsc_2366_b001_006; Poussin, Nicolas, 1594-1665; French drawing. Pen and bistre.; 6.5 x 8.5 cm.
  Acquired in 1952.
  On one page with five drawings. Drawing one of five.
- Aurora and Cupid, 17th century; lsc_2366_b001_007; Poussin, Nicolas, 1594-1665; French drawing. Pen and bistre.; 8.3 x 14.2 cm.
  On one page with five drawings. Drawing two of five.
- Offer, 17th century; lsc_2366_b001_008; Poussin, Nicolas, 1594-1665; French drawing. Pen and bistre.; 8.2 x 13.8 cm.
  On one page with five drawings. Drawing three of five.
- Dance composition, 17th century; lsc_2366_b001_009; Poussin, Nicolas, 1594-1665; French drawing. Pen and bistre.; 8.8 x 13 cm.
  On one page with five drawings. Drawing four of five.
- Rural scene, 17th century; lsc_2366_b001_010; Poussin, Nicolas, 1594-1665; French drawing. Pencil and gray wash.; 7 x 13 cm.
  On one page with five drawings. Drawing five of five.
- Portrait of Leonardo da Vinci, 18th-19th century; lsc_2366_b001_011; French drawing. After portrait in the editio princeps (1651) of the Trattato della pittura.; 13 x 10.2 cm.
  Collection Seeborger; Eric Bifferd; Jules Dapan sale Paris 1840; gift of Robert Schadt, curator, Huntington Library.
- Adoration of the Magi, 1869; lsc_2366_b001_012; Degas, Edgar, 1834-1917; Pencil on slightly yellowed paper.; 21 x 2 x 21.7 cm.
  Atelier Degas, 4 et derniere vente, Paris, Galeries George Petit, July 2-4, 1919, no.85b (repr.); acquired by B. Degenhart in Munich, 1949 or 1951, for the Belt Library.
  Inscribed in upper right-hand corner in pencil: "Florence 1869. Leonardo da Vinci." In lower left-hand corner is the red stamp Degas of the Durand Duel inventory after Degas' death. J. Rewald dates 1860, but Degas was in Italy in 1869.
  K.T. Steinitz, in Raccolta Vinciana XX(1964):387-390, fig. 1; Pedretti (op. cit. in I.1), pp. 43ff.
- Self-portrait in oval, 18th-19th century; lsc_2366_b005_001; Morghen, Raffaello, 1761-1833; Italian engraving.; 32 x 23 cm.
- Man with goitre and pointed nightcap, 17th century; lsc_2366_b005_002; Ribera, Jusepe de, 1591-1652; Spanish engraving.; 21.9 x 14.5 cm.
  Monogram at left corner: "JR". Cut sharply at frameline.
  Bartsch XX pp. 82f. No. 99
- Profile of man with bandaged head or turban, 17th century; lsc_2366_b005_003; Ribera, Jusepe de, 1591-1652; Spanish engraving.; 14.5 x 11.5 cm.
  Monogram at right corner: "SP 1022". Cut at frameline.
  Bartsch XX p. 82 No.8.
- Woman examining an armillary sphere, 16th century; lsc_2366_b005_004; Master FP; German(?) drypoint etching. After Parmigianino.; 10.5 x 8 cm, matted on 23 x 17.6 cm
  Inscribed NEDIMEON [sic: Endimion]. Signed on plate F.P. On verso penciled reference: Mazzuoli 1320 (F.P.) B.20 [=Bartsch XX]. F.P. refers to the signature on the plate. Aus dem Kupferstich-Kabinett des Fuersten Waldburg Wolfegg (according to stamp and penciled note on verso of the print). Sale of duplicates 1902/1903.
  Bartsch XVI p. 25 No. 2; cf. pp. 4f. on FP.
- Annunciation, 16th century; lsc_2366_b005_005; Parmigianino, 1503-1540; Italian drypoint etching.; 11.5 x 7 cm.
  Mounted on blue. Signed on plate, the letters appearing reversed on the print. On verso: Stamp. Fuerstl. Waldburg Wolffeggsches Kupferstichkabinett (Lugt, Supplement No. 2542, p. 476). Below: B2 gegenseitig 117. Above in pencil: 161-321.
  Bartsch XVI pp. 6f. No. 2.
- La morte de Leonard de Vinci, 19th century; lsc_2366_b005_006; Bonington, Richard Parkes, 1801-1828; English engraving.; Impression: 16 x 20 cm on 22 x 27.5 cm.
  Left: R.P. Bonington del. Right: F. Courbion sc. Below: La mort de Leonaro de Vinci. Printed by Lemercier and Cie., Paris, in the series: L'artiste. Lower right corner in pencil: Richard Park Bonington, engl. geb. 1801.
- Adam, 1529; lsc_2366_b005_007; Beham, Hans Sebald, 1500-1550; German woodcut.; 12 x 11.8 cm and 4.8 x 12.2 cm.
  Mainz, 1529.
  Bartsch VII p. 114 (gives 1519 and: "On a deux epreuves differentes de ces deux morceaux").
- Eve, 1529; lsc_2366_b005_008; Beham, Hans Sebald, 1500-1550; German woodcut.; 12 x 11.8 cm and 4.8 x 12.2 cm.
- The Death of Leonardo da Vinci, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_009; Walker, William, 1729-1793, engraver.; English engraving.; 12 x 17.5 cm.
  Cut and mounted on stationery paper. On verso a handwritten poem on widow-burning in India. Right: Walker sculp. Top: European magazine. Below: The Death of Leonardo de Vincay, publ. Sep. 1 1784 by Fielding, Paternoster Row (London) L. Sewell, Cornhill & I. Debrett, Picadilly.
- Portrait of Benvenuto Cellini with hat, undated; lsc_2366_b005_010; Engraving.; 11 x 6 cm. Impression: 14.8 x 9.4 cm on 22 x 14 cm.
  Taken from a book printed in England.
- Portrait, probably of Francesco d'Este, undated; lsc_2366_b005_011; Della Bella, Stefano, 1610-1664; Italian engraving.; 17 x 12.2 cm.
  Cut sharp at frameline. Portrait in an oval within an elaborate cartouche with inscription: Franciscvs ex Principibus / Etruriae. The portrait represents a young man in armor with a lace collar.
  J. Bialostocki, European painting in Polish collections, describes as after a portrait by Velasquez in Modena, Bibl. Estense; cf. Wittkower, Bernini catalogue, no. 54.
- Inclined head of a woman, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_012; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 2 of first edition. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
  Raccolta di disegni incisi...sugli originali esistenti nella Biblioteca Ambrosiana di Milano di Leonardo da Vinci e dei suoi scolari (1785).
- Male profile, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_013; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 4 of first edition. Windsor 12453. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Caricature heads, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_014; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engravings. Three black, one sanguine.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 7 of first edition. Windsor 12491, 12493 a.o. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Three caricature heads, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_015; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engravings.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 8 of first edition. Windsor 12554, lower part of Salai profile. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Female profile, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_016; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 11 of first edition. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Two apostles, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_017; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 12 of first edition. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Caricatures, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_018; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving. Sanguine.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 16 of first edition. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Profile of a bearded young man, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_019; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 14 of first edition. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Man with windblown hair, 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_020; Mantelli, Girolamo; Italian engraving.; 30.5 x 25.5 cm.
  No. 5 of first edition. Marked on plate HM, the number of the first edition of 1785 (Verga No. 50). On each leaf, upper right corner, in pencil, the date 1842.
- Profile study of a man's head, 16th century; lsc_2366_b005_021; Beham, Hans Sebald, 1500-1550; German engraving.; 5 x 8 cm.
  Two studies of man's profile, the left one with proportion lines possibly derived from Leonardo; above at the second head, on a white band: "Eines Mannes Haupt." Between the heads, centered, a small cartouche touching the lower margin; with date and monogram: 1542 HS B.
  Gustav Pauli, Hans Sebald Beham: ein kritisches Verzeichnis seiner Kupferstiche, Radirungen und Holzschnitte (Strassburg: Heitz, 1901) III: 320; Bartsch VIII p. 211 No. 219.
- Caricature head, engraved in a circle within a square, undated; lsc_2366_b005_022; French engraving.; 7.5 x 7 cm on 9 x 8.4 cm.
  Left: Leonardo da Vinci. Right: De la Collection du Prince Charles de Ligne. Below: Dedie a ma femme. Engraved inscription around the circle: "Leonardo de Vinci de la collection du Prince de Ligne."
- Sheet of 19 caricature heads, circa 18th century; lsc_2366_b005_023
  Italian. Unattributed: Casolani.
- Florence, ca. 1550. A pictorial map of the walled city., 16th century; lsc_2366_b007_001; Italian engraving.; 31.4 x 44.5 cm.
  Mounted on gray and matted 54 x 69 cm. Top, centered: Fiorenza [letter z in reverse]. Left: Medici coat of arms. Right: Florentine fleur-de-lis within small cartouche. In foreground the river with the word: Arno. 5 cm. to lower margin: list of 60 buildings numbered according to numbers on map.
- Series of three small handcolored maps, undated; VII.2-4; Italian engravings.; 9.4 x 15 cm on 14 x 21 cm.
  VII.2 Brescia VII.3 Cremona VII.4 Ferrara
- Map of Dukedom of Milan, 1670; lsc_2366_b007_005; Ortelius, Abraham, 1527-1598; Dutch engraving.; 36 x 48.5 cm.
  Acquired in 1947 from Bennet (c)
  Title in cartouche at left: Ducatus / Mediolanen / sis, finitima- / rumq 3 regionv / descriptio, avc- / tore Ioanne Ge- / orgio Septalia mediola / nense. / Top right: Sforza coat of arms. Verso: printed: p. 76 of Ortelius atlas 1670: Le Duche de Milan.
- Map of Florentine dominion, circa 17th century; lsc_2366_b007_006; Blaeu, Joan, 1596-1673; Blaeu, Cornelis, 1610-1648; Dutch engraving.; 39 x 50 cm. (map and impression)
  Title in decorative cartouche: Domino / Fioren / tino. Left lower corner: small cartouche with coat of arms with dedication to "D. Theodoro Hasselaer. Scala di Mielia quindici." Between map and frameline a band with measurements. Represents Tuscany west of Florence with Empoli and Vinci.
- Map of Touraine, France, 17th century; lsc_2366_b007_007; Blaeu, Willem Janszoon, 1571-1638; Blaeu, Joan, 1596-1673; Dutch engraving.; 37.5 x 49 cm, 46.5 x 55 cm.
  Old hand coloring. Above right within a garlanded vignette: Ducatus / Tyronensis / perlustratus e descriptus ab / Isaaco Franco, Aedili Regia / et in ea provincia viarum magistro / (line) Touraine. Above left: (...Below left: Scale within a vignette. Gallica commune: Right below: Apud Guiljelmia et Johannem Blaew Amsteldami. On verso: printed text with titles: Ducatvs / Tvorenensis / vulgo Duche de Touraine.
- Reproduction of Mappamondo Catalano della Estense, undated; lsc_2366_b007_008
  Modern (lithographic?) reproduction of circa 1375 piece.
- Large male head en face, 18th century; lsc_2366_b007_009; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Italian engraving. After Leonardo da Vinci.; 30.5 x 20 cm. Impression: 35 x 25.2 cm. on 57 x 40.5 cm.
  Below left: From the original drawing by Leonardo da Vinci. Below right: Engraved by Fl Bartolozzi, R.A. Historical Engraver to his Majesty. Below middle: In His Majesty's Collection published as the act directs...1796 by Chamberlaine.
- Mona Lisa, undated; lsc_2366_b007_010; Modern (lithographic?) color reproduction.
  Original creator: Leonardo da Vinci.
- Portrait, undated; lsc_2366_b007_011; Modern (lithographic?) color reproduction with Russian captions.
  Original creator: Francesco Melzi.
- Christi Erklaerung ueber das Vornehmste Gebot, 1808; lsc_2366_b007_012; Bause, Johann Friedrich, 1738-1814; German engraving.
  Below left: Fr. Bause sculp. 1808.
- Mort de Leonard de Vinci peint par Ingres, grave par Richemine., undated; lsc_2366_b007_013; Richemine; French engraving.; 39 x 49.3 cm on 47.3 x 58.5 cm.
  Copy 2 acquired in Rome in 1969 by Kate Traumann Steinitz and donated to the library.
  Imprime et publie par Goupl et Cie. Paris, London, Berlin, Verlag von Goupil et Cie. New York, published by M. Knoedler. 2 copies. With: Announcement of the sale of the painting, signed and dedicated to Alexander von Humboldt, 1881.
- Les Quatres banquets, circa 1619; VII.15-18; Callot, Jacques, 1592-1635; French engravings.
  VII.15 Noce de Cana. 5 x 5.5 cm (L.295) VII.16 Le repas chez le Parisien. (L.296) VII.17 Super d'Emaus. 5 x 5.4 cm (L.288) VII.18 La Cene. (X)
  Presentation tipped in at left margin: "To Dr. Elmer Belt, great Vincian and great friend this triumph of Jacques Callot done in Florence in 1619. Herbert M. Evans." Paris: Chez Jean, rue Jean de Beauvais, no. 32.
- [Sections of skeletons], 18th century; lsc_2366_b007_019; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Italian engraving. After Leonardo da Vinci.
  Below left: from the original drawing by Leonardo da Vinci. Below right: engraved by F. Bartolozzi, R.A. Historical Engraver to his Majesty. Below middle: In His Majesty's collection...
- Leonardo Portrait, 18th century; lsc_2366_b006_004; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Italian engraving. Sanguine.; 28 x 19.5 cm. Impression: 32 x 25 cm. on 42.5 x 34 cm.
  Windsor 12726. Frontispiece. Tuer: 677-(1). Left: From the original drawing by Hans Holbein [sic]. Right: engraved by F. Bartolozzi, R.A. Historical Engraver to His Majesty. Below: in His Majesty's collection, published as the Act directs. Sept. 1, 1795 by I. Chamberlaine.
  Chamberlaine 1796.
- A youth's head in profile (Salai), 18th century; lsc_2366_b004_002; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Italian engraving. Sanguine.; 21.5 x 15 cm. Impression: 29 x 24 cm on 38 x 29 cm.
  Windsor 12554. Pl. 3 erroneously listed as "Woman's head." Tuer: - Right: Engraved by F. Bartolozzi, R.A. Historical Engraver to His Majesty. Left: From the original drawing by Leonardo da Vinci. Below: In His Majesty's Collection/published October 1, 1796 by John Chamberlain...In pencil: right lower corner 1/50.
  Chamberlaine 1812.
- Half-length figure in profile, seated, undated; lsc_2366_b004_003; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Italian engraving. Red stippel [stippling?]; 18 x 13 cm. Impression: 29 x 23.8 cm, on 3 x 2 cm with 5 frame lines.
  Windsor 12584 (copy). Pl. 6. Tuer" 684 (8).
- Young man leaning, 18th century; lsc_2366_b004_004; Bartolozzi, Francesco, 1727-1815; Italian engraving. Sanguine.; 23.5 x 18.5 cm. Impression: 28 x 23 cm on 36 x 27.5 cm.
  No. - Tuer: - Right below: in pencil by a later hand: F. Bartolozzi. In left corner of impression: in pencil: LP.